So exciting.
Today is February 2, 2026.
My name is Caitlin Sheets, and I'm currently in the glass clock building, is that right?
In the basement.
I'm here with Lauren Huntley, and we're conducting this interview on Texas A&M's campus and College Station.
The interview is part of the oral history project documenting the experiences of Aggies for the 150th celebration of Texas A&M.
Do I consent to report?
Yes.
Awesome.
Thank you so much.
So I'm here with Lauren Huntley, as I said, a former undergrad
I was a current grad student as well as an employee.
That's awesome.
Thank you for joining me and sharing your story.
Of course.
I'm so happy to be here.
Thank you.
Can you give me a little bit of background before you came to Texas A&M?
Yeah.
Yeah, so I was born in Cincinnati.
I come from rural Ohio people.
I still say pop, all that good stuff.
There was a scary week there with the college playoffs because A&M would have gone to Ohio State if we beat Miami.
But alas, Carson Beck made that not an issue.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I always imagined I'd go back up to Ohio for school.
All my extended family is still up there.
My dad went to Miami University in Oxford, Ohio.
My mom went to Ohio State for a semester before going to cosmetology school.
So a lot of roots are in Ohio.
We moved down here 20 years ago this summer, which is crazy.
We went to Sugar Land, Missouri City area.
I was there in elementary school until fifth grade.
And then we moved to the Woodlands.
I was there fifth through...
You know, until I went to college.
Yeah, I have two siblings.
One's a twin sister who did not pursue higher ed at all.
And then my brother who went to A&M who kind of fed me the Kool-Aid.
Yes, my sister and I visited him one weekend and I was like,
This isn't so bad.
Yeah, sure.
And then after high school, I was encouraged slash you're going to do Lone Star Community College for a year.
I only had to do it a year instead of two to get my full associate since I graduated high school with like 27 college credits.
Yeah, my high school is a very, very huge proponent for AP, dual credits, the Woodlands High School.
Yes.
Yeah, we're a 6A.
It's, it's hard to explain, but everything's competition and the woodlands.
Like if you, yes, it is.
If you want to do varsity or be the lead in the, I did theater in high school.
So if you wanted to do leads, I was on the improv troupe in high school.
I was the president for two years and it was pretty much, you have to start doing that when you're five for a chance.
Cause it's a 6A.
I graduated with 1100 kids.
So it's a different culture.
Yes, it's very competitive, academics and athletics equally.
I think that's kind of hard to find, but again, it's Texas, so yeah.
present in your mind yes I wouldn't say though I tried in high school English and English particularly became very very easy to me I was always a really big reader as a kid I have a edition of Little House on the Prairie on my bookshelf um that is a good example of why I am the way I am today the the breadcrumbs were always always there um I just I originally was actually going to study English um but they recommended to transfer into A&M you already have your foreign language done and I did not
And so the BS of history here at A&M offers without the foreign language.
And that was the only other major I was interested in.
So I kind of naturally went in there.
I want to say that might have been the first year they offered that.
So the timing was very, very kismet.
And I'm very, very thankful.
And I was an English minor.
So it's still a big part of my life.
It's a big philosophy of my history training and all that.
But yeah.
Yeah.
Academics have always been a big part of me.
It's definitely been, I was embarrassed to get B's.
I was that kid in English who, like, if Lauren didn't read, we're screwed.
Like, I'd always be that person.
Yeah, math and science are always pretty hard for me.
I never really... Yeah, I never really got that, but...
teacher professor that really encouraged you yeah I had a wonderful junior and senior so both of those were dual credits um Dr. Heidi Bardenhagen was my junior and then um Dr. no he's not a doctor sorry uh Jeff Murren was my senior and like he used to be the only teacher who taught senior year dual credits so it was like my brother had him when he taught at McCullough the junior high school so then he moved to the high school he's just amazing he's tatted up and he's just awesome and
I love that man.
He's just wonderful, wonderful.
And Dr. Barton Hagen, obviously overqualified.
Just tried everything to make sure we knew the more analytical side of English.
And it's not just the curtains were blue, which symbolizes sadness.
Like it was.
Yeah, but she was unfortunately
ran out of the woodlands.
She was teaching lenses of English, and one of them is a Marxist lens.
She was not saying she's a huge Marxist, but there was a kid who was part of the Turning Point USA club.
He brought that to parents, and she was alleviated of her duties.
That's wild.
Yeah, absolutely.
But that's still happening.
Absolutely.
That was 2023?
2023.
2023 would still be the Marxist is scary.
The thing is...
It's the most frustrating because she left academia because she said it focused too much on research and she just wanted to teach.
That's so rare.
No, I know.
And she could have gone to a private or a small liberal arts school, but she chose dual credit English.
Yeah.
I really credit them too for, you know, like if I do defend successfully my PhD, like I would definitely make sure to knock on wood to find them and be like, you are a huge part of this.
So.
seeing where it comes from oh yeah no totally and like so i particularly focus on native american history and i was torn between that or holocaust studies two very uh light-hearted areas of history um but growing up my parents favorite movie one of theirs is dances with wolves
And obviously it's not historically the best, but it was just always kind of in the background or my parents are really big history fans, maybe not in the academic sense, but more of just in popular culture or a documentary.
My mom's a huge reader, so it's always been encouraged to, you know, listen to the real quote unquote real story or
Give space for that.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
Can I ask if your parents are educated?
Yeah.
My father went to Miami University.
It is in Oxford, Ohio.
I almost went there.
I was accepted, but it was $30,000 for out-of-state.
Not really worth that.
But yeah, my dad, he majored in sports management, but now he is the VP of an automobile company for supply chain.
So just because you get a degree in something doesn't mean that's what you have to do.
And then my mom went to Ohio State for a semester before she went to cosmetology school.
So me being A&M, graduating, very, very big deal.
My mom does not take this for granted and really instilled that in me and Rachel, my twin sister,
try to do something because yeah that's yeah no that's the one thing that you really can't get taken away from you is that education and the skills you learn in the classroom that's very true um so come from a very academic family or even even seems like a hard looking yes yes um so did you ever feel a lot of pressure or have those
No, I never felt like if I didn't bring home an A, I'd be grounded for a month.
It was more of just don't be a dumbass.
It's kind of expected of just you excel.
You know, I was never pressured to have an actual job in high school.
School was the job.
So it was just try to never to quit at anything.
You make a commitment.
You got to do it.
That was as well as theater and improv.
Just give 110% to everything you do.
My mom's dad farmed for 40 years, so...
Yeah.
Hardworking.
Do you think that those traits have followed you through?
Mm-hmm.
I think just not taking it for granted.
I think sometimes you see kids on campus who college to them was never a question.
It's just something they have to do to check off the box and maybe they're not appreciating of like, this might be the one time in my life where I just get to read something and talk about it and try to expand yourself as a human, as a scholar.
I think that's so, so, so special.
And I think it's maybe the first time
in a lot of society's history where a majority of its populace are educated, literate, and trying to improve in that area.
Very good point.
So we talked a little bit about this, about where history came from.
What made you choose Native American history?
Yeah, I can tell you exactly.
So I was taking Native American history, a little survey course with Dr. Angela Hudson.
I was in M207, this building over here on campus.
It's the A in engineering.
For some reason, a lot of history seminars are in there.
It's like a huge 400-person seminar room.
And I just remember sitting there one day, and I'm like, this is what I want to do.
um obviously it's not a i'm an outsider i am not indigenous culturally um related i'm not enrolled in any federally recognized tribes or state recognized tribes um but it makes you view america in maybe a different light a more more honest more truthful it's a harder light to look at it but it makes you feel more connected to the land its people its cultures um
Yeah, and it's, you know, not typically the first thing or maybe in bold when you read textbooks.
Maybe it's a little side and then once we get to the Trail of Tears, it's never really brought up again.
And that's something I'm very passionate about is bringing it into the main historical conversation.
Yeah, I mean, yeah.
And Dr. Hudson is now serving as my advisor.
So it's full circle.
It was just a once in a lifetime opportunity.
Really, really, really.
Yeah.
Um, was the first time you met her was in that class?
Yes.
But it's pretty, it's a bigger class.
So I don't know if we ever got a lot on one-on-one time.
And then, um, that following semester, so fall, no, spring of 23.
Yeah.
Spring of 23.
Um, she was teaching her smaller 300 level class called Native Americans of the South.
And I took that as well.
And again, just completely fall in love with it.
I would consider myself a Southern historian.
Um,
And I actually met a future roommate there.
Yeah, like, yeah, like just has overfull in my cup in so many ways.
But that's when we definitely had a way closer intimate working relationship.
And then that summer, I was graduating early in August.
So I'm class of 25, but graduated.
May, no, August to 24.
So I'm like a full year early.
And I basically reached out to her and said like, hey, I need a job.
Like, do you need someone to refill coffee?
Like anything, anything, anything I will do for you.
And she said like, I was actually about to reach out to you.
I need a research assistant for a project.
And that's what kind of got me on board to do actual...
factual history and not just reading about it.
I was researching a group of Native Americans who were here between 1904 to 1911.
They were football players here before we officially integrated.
And it's transnational.
We're dealing with people from Oklahoma.
We have a Cheyenne individual.
They're from Carlisle, the boarding school in Carlisle, Pennsylvania.
Again, just completely transforms what you think of A&M when we realize who was actually here taking classes before maybe we were in that national.
Right, yeah.
Attention spotlight?
Yeah.
So we worked on that research together for a year.
We presented a paper together at the Alliance for Texas History conference in May of 25.
That was my first conference.
And then I basically told her, like, hey, I'm applying for a PhD.
Like, I really want to do this for the rest of my life.
fills me, like this is amazing.
So yeah, here we are.
I am finished with my first semester as of fall of 25, and now we're entering spring 26.
Congratulations.
Yes, well thank you.
Actually, can you go back and talk a little bit about the Native Americans that were here before?
Yeah.
Because I had no knowledge.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So we found six in this time frame.
All of them but one are Choctaw, which we think there might be something there.
And the other one I mentioned, Cheyenne, his name is Michael Valenti.
He is actually related from someone who survived wounded knee.
His mother survived wounded knee.
And he actually went on to marry, she's Alaskan native.
Her name is Cecilia Baranovich, and her dad was actually a Russian trapper mogul.
So...
Insane.
And Michael went on after being here at A&M.
He coached for Baylor.
He had an amazing career in the minor league baseball as well as professionals.
He was part of the Cincinnati Reds for a little bit, so that was...
As a Cincinnati native, that was fun.
And then we also have George Marlowe.
He was also Choctaw.
Oh gosh, we have Sig Flincham, James Flincham, nicknamed Sig, who we think is married during his time here, which is odd because where was his wife staying?
So unfortunately, a lot more questions are not answered with these men because there's a lot of questions about if they're being paid or not.
Oh.
because we have records of michael balenti and um victor kelly called by chalk as he's choctaw chalk kelly being paid at carlisle so it's kind of hard to imagine why they would leave their income to texas when they have absolutely no ties right here um what years is this i'm sorry yeah no you're right it's between about 1904 to 1911 okay yes and this is a football period in which we have the head coach of um
Charles Moran, Uncle Charlie.
Yes.
So this is the only other time where A&M stopped playing UT.
There was claims that he had professionals, which might have been those Carlisle native players, if they're being paid.
And basically they said, we're not playing you until Moran's gone.
And we didn't play them for three years.
That's wild.
So, yeah, we have a lot of evidence of them being involved in clubs.
They were very active in Ross Volunteers, which is ironic, as Sol Ross is a proclaimed, quote-unquote, Indian killer.
Yet he has indigenous people probably honoring him and his memory and his impact at Texas A&M.
They are part of the glee club.
They are known as, quote, ladies men with these white women in Bryan.
So it raises questions of interracial relationships.
So yeah, it's very exciting.
It's probably what's going to be my master's thesis.
So yeah, just fascinating.
That was just a person, for me personally.
Because I'm trying to put different pieces of this puzzle together from an outsider.
There's so many pieces that just don't make sense yet.
So there was a fire in 1912 that...
like did away with the old main building, which has all of our records of where they slept, which I need to know, just a lot of those records that unfortunately are lost that would probably answer a lot of those questions.
Um, but yeah.
Do you want me to, I have over 2000 world histories from Aggies, their wives, don't they go through those and see what I, yes please.
Also you can have access to them.
Okay.
Thank you so much.
Yeah.
Um, because this,
Yes, so Chuck Kelly and Mike Valenti are probably the two biggest successes in terms of their football career while they're here.
They were nominated for like a Southwest all-time, who would be the best team.
Both of them are on it.
Victor Kelly went on to live in LA after.
He was a PE coach for like 50 years at Hollywood High School.
That's wonderful.
And then he actually was a technical advisor for one of Judy Garland's first films, Pigskin Parade.
Texas State accidentally gets picked to play Yale in the championship, so they have to rally the troop, rally the men.
Yeah, I actually got in contact with his granddaughter, Linda, so that was an amazing phone call.
That's awesome.
So yeah.
Yeah.
No, it really does change.
You know, sometimes I think with the Southern schools, you think a very specific group of people were sitting at that table.
And I think constantly looking at, is that true?
Right.
We have records of women taking classes here.
Before.
Before the 20th century.
Yep.
And as well as Mexican-American.
Absolutely.
Mexican-American.
So many Central Americans.
So many.
We have so many ags from India.
I mean, it's crazy, crazy, crazy.
And they're proudly in these yearbooks because the most interesting thing about my native ags, which I forgot to mention, none of them graduated until Bill Leftwich in 1954.
So they're here for four years plus.
None of them have officially graduated.
We think that might have been they're only taking a class or two.
But then this is at a time when the whole school is working on the core schedule.
So what are you doing all day?
What are you doing all day?
Very strict.
Yeah.
I mean, there's in the yearbook of like what time breakfast is, what time march is, what time is everyone walking the fourth period?
Like it's a very military school.
It 100 percent is.
So we just want to know, did that cause animosity?
Well, clearly not, because Victor Kelly was awarded most popular cadet for superlatives in one of the yearbooks.
So these are very well-known people on campus.
So it is fascinating that there is no sign of them today.
When arguably the beginnings of A&M football being commercially successful is this team.
Yes, it is.
Because I'm a football nut.
I really am.
I obviously the amount of money the school's invested into it.
I think that's partly why of like, okay, well, if there's some areas of the school that are not as funded, but we're putting hundreds of million dollars into our coaching salaries and NIL and our facilities.
I'm going to check in.
Obviously, there's a lot of literature on native sport, obviously with Jim Thorpe and, you know, Carlisle football team completely transformed the game as we know it.
So they're very, very interconnected and related.
So it's very exciting.
Another side thing.
I think we just, not inherited, but we're now housing all of the old films.
Reels?
Mm-hmm.
From the football?
Do you?
Mm-hmm.
Yep, okay.
I'm going to cry.
Oh!
Because there's photos.
We have photos of them playing these games sometimes, and it's like just being able to pick them out.
Right.
Because only Victor Kelly, I'd say, is phenotypically someone you could appoint as indigenous.
Mm-hmm.
So there's something to that.
Very much.
And they're calling him Choctaw.
They are not hiding their nativeness.
In the yearbook, they hail, oh, he's from the new state of Oklahoma.
He does the corn dance.
He does the war whoops.
But it's fascinating.
The more they become integrated into campus, the less they comment on their nativeness.
That's interesting.
So we kind of question, is this Aggie, the binding force, is this able to trump racial lines?
There's something to that.
That's strong.
Yeah, there's something to that.
There truly is.
Yeah.
This is also going to be a random side thing, but you brought up the Aggie spirit.
Mm-hmm.
And I've seen, or I've heard so many different people say what it means to them.
What does that mean to you?
I would say really and truly just taking the harder path, if it's the right path.
I would say that is probably the Aggie way.
Like, why am I getting choked up?
My parents were at the airport the other day.
They didn't go to A&M, but they were wearing A&M merch.
And they saw a young mom, just alone, just kind of struggling.
We had a toddler crying and, like, another kind of pulling on her arm.
And she's obviously having a hard time.
And my mom just walks up to her and says, like, can I hold?
Do you need to go to the bathroom or something?
And we can watch them.
And she said, like, well, y'all are Aggies.
Of course.
Mm-hmm.
So, you know, and I know people make fun of it, of cult or whatever, but you can go anywhere, anywhere, anywhere, and you will find someone.
And that is just enough to share a meal or lend a helping hand.
And I think that is so, so, so important today.
That's so powerful.
Truly.
Yeah.
And I hear all these stories about people that they're giving their senior ring.
Oh, yeah.
And then they see somebody else in the wild with it, and they just instantly have that connection.
Yeah, yeah.
all is very new.
Oh, absolutely.
Yeah, it is a whole new world.
And part of it breaks my heart because I want to say out of the 12 of my cohort for grad school, maybe only two of us went to undergrad here.
So they don't love it like we do.
It doesn't maybe mean as much to them.
You know, they came here specifically for a professor or maybe the stipend was the most handsome or something like that.
So they didn't get to really experience all the charm that A&M has to offer.
So, yeah, I do try to, you know, amp it up or say, like, you really should go to a football game.
Like, you're here.
Baseball is super fun.
The whole town doesn't shut down for baseball.
It's easier to get in and out.
And, you know, our women volleyball team just brought home our first national title.
And it's just very exciting.
Basketball is doing good.
I had no idea what that would look like.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, it's just a very, very exciting time.
Athletic.
Athletically, yes.
Yes, athletically.
So obviously you were interested in history as an undergraduate, but what made you continue on as that?
Dr. Hudson.
Yes, Dr. Hudson.
Native Studies is kind of a smaller area.
My husband's also getting his master's at A&M in engineering.
I joke A&M owns us, but we just bought a house here.
We're putting roots down.
We're guaranteed here for five years with my program.
So it just makes the most sense.
He also works full-time, so I did not apply to anywhere else.
This is it?
Yes, and I only applied out of Lone Star Community College to A&M.
That's impressive.
People say don't do that.
I've got a lot of people say do not do that for undergrad and graduate, but I knew.
If you love it, you love it.
I love it.
So, yeah, I'll be an ag for, oh gosh, undergrad was three.
Yeah, almost eight years.
Almost a decade.
Yeah.
You're almost an old ag now.
Almost old ag, yeah.
It's funny to me that the agies that I've talked to, when they...
they didn't go here, but they came as a professor or something.
And they say, they don't, they feel like they can't claim being an Aggie.
And I'm like, you taught here for 25 years.
That makes me sad.
It makes me sad because you're shaping these Aggies.
They're learning how, what that Aggie spirit work ethic looks like through you and the rigor that you are demanding from them.
That's 110% part of it.
Yeah, that upsets me.
makes me really sad yeah i hear no i mean yeah i didn't go to miami or ohio state but you know you feel that connection through family or through just being associated with it for time so i think i have no problem if you teach your room right yeah or like even i encourage grad kids to get their ag hearing why wouldn't you
I know it's expensive.
You put in the work and it's a wonderful tradition that not every school honors.
I mean, we have one of the highest graduation rates in Texas.
Absolutely.
Yes, absolutely.
I want to say we're in the nineties now.
If not 90s, 80s.
And that's unheard of.
That's unheard of.
Absolutely.
Like, I don't think I've literally heard of universities like that.
No, because it is, it's a part.
If you say to someone, I went to A&M and you don't see their ring, you ask, well, is it getting resized?
What's wrong?
Is something wrong?
It's a part of it.
It's 110% part of it.
I mean, I have a paperweight.
Like when Will, my husband got his Agering, my brother got his Agering, and me, my mom, there's this Etsy seller that makes like a wooden ornament of it with your year.
Yeah, like 110%.
Yeah.
So your brother, what was his deal?
Parks and Rec.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Yes, we put the and in A and M. We are not A or M, but yes.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Does he work at an actual park?
So he actually just accepted a new job.
We're very, very excited for him.
He is an aquatics man.
So he runs and pretty much makes sure that lifeguards are being trained properly.
Equipment is good.
Patrons are happy.
Pools are clean.
It's running smoothly.
That's what he does.
He did that for the Woodlands Township for 10 years.
He was there from 16 to 25.
And now he just moved to San Antonio for that.
So he's doing 23 facilities, one year-round natatorium.
We could not be more excited for him.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
That's amazing.
So Dr. Hudson, what, okay, she also is Native American studies as well, right?
Yes.
Okay.
So what is her teaching style?
Because I've never taken a quiz here, obviously.
Yeah.
So I would definitely say she is trying to get you prepared for asking questions that you just have to approach every single text with, every single primary document with, in every single archive trip.
What am I asking?
Who wrote it?
Where do they go to school?
Who's their advisor?
It's all connected.
She really stresses that.
What sources are they engaging in?
What secondary sources?
Who's she pushing back on?
Whose work are they building upon or who are they kind of disputing?
When you go into an archive, it can be simple as take a picture of what you want and then write a little note to yourself because you're going to forget in two weeks why you took a photo of that.
She taught me...
try to be kind to your future forgetful self.
She says that sometimes and I always try to remember that.
She's very primary based.
Oh yeah, in our 300 level class, she'd have a worksheet of like, okay, pull out a line, explain the source they got this from.
Is this a good interpretation of the source?
You don't see that a lot in history classes at like those levels.
It's mainly, again, I think it's just a misconception of the history field in general of just regurgitating a timeline or something that we completely diverge from past 100 level class, especially here at A&M.
But yeah, she's a wonderful, wonderful person to learn how to dissect, look at that document in the context.
How does that impact?
She also comes with an English background.
She has a master's in English as well.
Um, so reading, I think reading.
Yeah.
And that's what a lot of my personal statement was for the grad program of like, I have a huge reading background.
I am a huge reader.
And I read to work in over at the English department was incredibly impactful to me.
Um, just meeting the source where it's at.
Right.
Yeah.
110%.
Um, when you were undergrad, you said you were English, correct?
um what professors there like what kind of skills were transferable to yeah so i was an english minor so i took um you know the comp and rec at the dual credit level in high school so then when i got here i took um oh gosh
A 19th century American novel with Ira DeWorkin, who's fabulous, who wrote a rec letter for me.
I took Chaucer with Dr. Britt Mize, all in Middle English.
I read The Canterbury Tales, all in Middle English.
That was fantastic.
And then with Dr. Cooper, I took...
American novel, World War II and on.
And as far as Dr. Orkin goes, again, just it's really easy to bring the 21st century with you when you're looking at stuff, when you're reading Uncle Tom's Cabin.
when you're reading um you know squatter in the dawn or something like that um when you're reading mark twain lord you want to you want to make it accessible to you but you just can't do that all the time and he would assign a healthy portion every night you'd come to class reading 100 pages each time and that does prep you for grad school but also just how can i read efficiently and effectively um and then brett mys
He was wonderful, and the very first day of class, it's a 400-level Chaucer class, and he said something in Middle English, basically saying, this is how it would sound.
And I swear to you, I heard two kids drop right then and there.
Like, I cannot do this.
Oh, my gosh.
Really, really stuck with me.
Just aspects of Chaucer.
You know, Canterbury Towels, it's literally...
a tale telling contest on a very serious pilgrimage so it's just between it's a balance between um earnest and game and that is where i really rest how i approach a grad seminar when i'm answering questions because i think academia is very very stuffy and unacceptable and it is this wall and it doesn't have to be so i try to always manage the earnestness and game and whatever i'm doing um
And then that last English class I took, there's a wonderful book called Sex and the Cherry by Jeanette Winterson.
It's a postmodernist work and it's just absurd and it's awesome.
And I highly recommend.
It's just good.
It's just good stuff.
And, you know, there's no one universal truth, all that good stuff post nihilism that you get from World War II.
So having you actually, on one hand, people say history is very one way linear.
And then on the other hand,
There is no one truth.
Yes.
How do you marry those two?
Yes, so I'm the latter.
I am no one truth, especially if you're an indigenous scholar, like indigenous studies scholar like myself, or if you focus on black history or Mexican-American history or any minority or marginalized history, you are not the spotlight.
So that dominant narrative, you can go, but all day.
And I think you have to accept that frustration that you have to meet that middle.
and it's maybe the more uncomfortable version but trying to be respectful to both sides and not just painting one as the villain and one as the savior that doesn't do anything good that isn't honest i yeah so it's difficult and it's frustrating there's people in my cohort who roll their eyes at what i do and it's fine um
Speaking more about that, the uncomfortableness in history, because there's facts and events that are uncomfortable.
What would you tell people who are uncomfortable when they're learning these things?
That's wonderful.
It means you're human.
I am so glad that you can walk through the Holocaust Museum and go, that's horrific in tears.
That means you're human.
Yeah.
I think expecting entertainment from history, okay, go to the movies for that.
If you want to feel good about history, that's just propaganda.
Read a book for that.
Read a fiction book for that.
I just don't think history is necessarily the outlet for entertainment, for pleasure, for, you know, if you're interested in the sublime, read Lovecraft.
You know what I mean?
It's just not, I think...
something that needs a casual viewing.
I think it's a very serious, almost sacred thing.
That doesn't mean that only learned people or the highest of people get to touch it or interact with it.
I am a huge proponent for public history, but I think it's the open mindedness of knowing that there's a million truths to this one statement.
And there's a million historians who would write that sentence completely differently.
And that's beautiful.
I find that beautiful.
actually yeah they're like we were explaining this um and for a student that i was teeing for and she said like what do you mean when we say historians debate the date things happen and i said okay 9 11 always happened on september 11 2001 we're not debating that we're debating
When did something start?
When did that movement end?
When did the war on terror end?
Who are the players involved?
That's what we're talking about.
So it's more of the nitty gritty details of that broader narrative and that broader history and story that we are debating and trying to find, you know, that smoking gun primary document that blows open or completely refutes the common accepted story.
That's what I think that is.
So that's, again, once you get past that 100%
level history class, you can start asking those questions.
But it's a good foundation.
At the end of the day, it is helpful to know the Louisiana Purchase, 1803.
There are dates that do help you, but it's not the end-all be-all.
That makes sense.
So someone from an outside, in our political climate right now, looking at all the different rhetoric that's going on, what are your thoughts on
So Texas A&M is a land-grant university.
That means the Morrill Act of 1863 granted these lands.
It comes from 183 tribal nations.
The mission of the land-grant university is equally agricultural mechanical, also the humanities.
That is tangent.
That is twofold.
They live in tandem together.
That has always been the joint mission.
You cannot have one without the other for a wholehearted liberal education.
Little L, not big L, liberal education.
And today, if you want to get specific with it, A&M doesn't stand for Agriculture Mechanical College of Texas anymore.
It's symbolic.
Rudder changed it to be symbolic.
We're honoring that past.
Today, I'm sure the most populated majors are ag and engineering.
That's fine.
But we're that and.
We're the ampersand.
You can't have one without the other.
It's a federal law that at Texas public universities, you have to take six credits of history.
makes a well-rounded education i think to be a informed voting participant in the body politic you have to know a certain level of things to know what your freedoms are granted to you that's just something you can't escape from in any history class um so does the current political climate scary yes i'm okay saying that um
And it hurts to know that Aggies are being turned away, being told they don't matter because of their academic desires and pursuits.
I think when we hear these certain buzzwords, a certain stereotype or caricature comes to mind.
And that's just not the case.
When you're sitting in these classrooms that are discussing these topics, you're not seeing the blue-haired angry woman
I'm married.
I am dirty blonde.
You're just, I think it's easier to create an enemy instead of sitting at that table together and having a conversation and banning certain works, banning certain topics.
They do not erase them.
They only create a drive to seek them somewhere else.
And wouldn't you rather them be discussed at Texas A&M with Texas A&M professors?
Very good point.
Making knowledge forbidden is never... Never.
I don't think it's historically ever... No, no.
You know, I try to look at what the Nazis did and try to maybe go the other way, but that's just me.
Very true.
So these really hard conversations, a lot of outside forces are...
They want to leave those conversations.
They just don't want to have them at all.
Yes.
From your, because you, your history, you have all the, like, that's what the, you look back at it.
Yes, yes.
Yeah, so, like, looking back at history, has that ever helped?
No.
no you're creating ignorance that's only going to infect your voting class and also most people who sit in the senate today are history majors because they're all lawyers okay so you're creating a dumber body if that's the point you're doing an amazing job but then you are just degrading what it means to be an aggie at the end of the day 110 percent you're making my degree less
and the thousands that came before me.
So.
Thank you for sharing that.
Of course.
No, no, I know it's hard, but I hope.
Again, if it has to come from someone, I'd rather it look like someone that maybe the people encouraging these views can align with.
Very good point.
Yeah.
So.
What would you say to undergrads who are interested in going to grad school, pursuing a line that you have, like following in your footsteps?
Yes.
So I found it to be completely different.
Completely different than an undergrad.
It is most of the time, at least in the history department, classes you meet once a week for three hours.
You're in a room with 12 people.
You find people that are 110% of themselves all the time, and they're such characters, and that's part of it.
And you're just in these rooms of people that you never would have met elsewhere.
And just being exposed to so many different worldviews or what they believe to be the truth or what is right, I think it feeds your soul.
Um, you know, I'm the first person in my family to pursue a higher graduate degree.
So that's kind of scary.
It's a little isolating.
You know, I talk about what I have to do or the amount I have to read or, you know, what the next steps look like.
And there's a proudness there.
They love the name of me being in this program, but actual nitty gritty details, I think maybe some of the lust, the luster wears off.
Um,
I never thought about that.
Yeah.
What do you do about that?
That feeling?
Oh, I just bite my tongue.
Because a lot of times if you're supporting party members who are doing this, who are infringing upon academic freedom, your daughter complaining about it, aw, that sucks.
What are you going to do?
Right.
Very true.
What are you going to do?
Because again, then it becomes, I'm a snooty academic.
I know more than you.
That's what the conversation becomes.
It becomes, I'm being brainwashed and out of A&M.
Yes, the pinnacle of leftist propaganda, Texas A&M.
Okay.
I don't care.
There is that big disconnect between academia and the everyday, quote unquote, everyday people.
How do you think we can bridge this?
very big no yeah no it is and I think it's what are we assigning in our high schools
Are we only assigning fiction works to connect our students to these?
Let's bust down a monograph, even if it's just reading the introduction.
I think it's not so jarring when students are interacting with it in high school and expecting to speak eloquently for a grade on it.
I think that will leave some pressure.
I think modeling high school more like college campuses.
I'm very lucky the Woodlands High School had an hour and 30 classes.
You only met four classes a day every other day.
I think that's more realistic.
I think there's some high schools that are 50 minutes.
You're going to die if you're in a Tuesday, Thursday hour and 30 class.
You just will.
Yeah, I would definitely say, what are we teaching before we get here?
And maybe it's on historians.
How am I writing?
Am I just writing to appease my adversary at a New England school that I'm jealous of?
So I'm using these big words when I don't have to?
That's not saying you have to dumb down your writing.
I think making your writing accessible is something everyone should strive for.
Absolutely.
Very much so.
I'm thinking about also the older generation as well.
Because...
It seems like we're having conversations at each other and not...
Yes, yes.
Yeah.
We're all having different conversations.
Absolutely.
Okay.
This is just a personal thought.
Yeah, no, yeah.
So having his story in front of me, I'm taking the chance to pick your mind about it.
What do we do about that?
If you want my honest to God answer, the world's going to look completely different when boomers die out.
I'm not wishing death upon yam yams.
I am not.
I have family that's in that generation.
I love them to death.
It's just a different world than they grew up in.
And it's a different world than I grew up in.
And that's okay.
That's just the passage of time.
That doesn't mean that what it means to be an American is any less, what it means to work hard is any less.
It's just, I think more now than ever, there's younger generations are okay with looking at something and saying that's wrong and saying it loudly.
And I think maybe part of it hurts to know that, you know, something might change and you won't reap the benefits of that.
You had to be the guinea pig that had to go through it when it was crappy.
There is a pain in that.
And I completely, like, I completely get that.
Yeah, very much so.
Yeah.
But I think a part of it definitely stems, my grandpa, like I said, he farmed and they were very intent on only having two kids.
to replace him and my grandma.
That's a very, not Western thinking, I'd argue.
Just making the world better when you left it.
And I don't think that's where we're at right now with older generations.
I think they're trying to extract the best they can while they're still here.
Maybe there is a fear in that.
But I also think, look at aging.
Look at the golden girls, how old they were when they started filming.
They're in their 40s and 50s.
Mm-hmm.
Look at a 40 and 50-year-old today.
It's completely different.
Very much.
Aging is different today.
Entertainment is different today.
Attention spans are different today.
Food is different today.
I just think there's anger in not recognizing the world you grew up for, died for, fought for, sacrificed for.
And I completely sympathize with that.
That's very valid.
Yeah.
But again, if...
I find comfort in talking to professionals in their own field about the way the world is and where we're going.
So seeing that gives me hope.
Yes, I think, you know, sometimes I have great responses and it doesn't give me hope.
Again, I'm meeting these kids in the very beginning of their academic journey most of the time.
And I find that so exciting.
So like that first response I just got from my TA class, I was doing line-by-line edits.
Because I'm like, when's the last time?
Because this kid was probably in high school post-COVID.
This kid probably never had a high school before COVID.
I would argue today, probably most teachers are teaching from an iPad.
They upload something to Canvas and say, have it done to me by the end of the day.
Most likely.
I didn't know that.
Yeah, that's the thing.
I've been in high school in so long.
But I mean, today we're teaching for test grades, standardized test grades for funding.
We're not teaching them how to phonetically talk anymore.
There's a literary crisis in elementary schools.
Kids don't know where they live.
Kids don't know their parents' names.
They don't know phone numbers.
It's a question of are we teaching our kids to check off a box or are we teaching kids to be critically thinking adults in the real world?
Where's I going with this?
Yeah, that's fine.
Well, dead in the water.
That's fine.
So you're a TA now, or actually fully teaching a class?
I am just a TA right now, so you have an option to be a gal, which is a graduate lecturer, when you are done, I want to say, with all your coursework as a PhD student.
And you get additional funding for that.
Yeah.
Exciting, scary, considering what I would teach.
Yes.
Yes, and I try to bring that to my parents.
And they're like, well, honey, you know.
For some reason, Native American history is okay to them.
Yeah, they don't.
My family does not see the pattern that I do that Native American history is on the chopping block.
Not now, not tomorrow, but it will be.
It 110% is.
Yeah.
It's not going to be narrative.
It's looking at the federal government and saying, they killed 300 people at Sand Creek.
It wasn't a battle.
It was a massacre.
And that's not comfortable.
It's not comfortable.
I had this conversation, almost exactly this conversation, with some of my own cohort when I was in grad school because I was in my very last year and they cut our program.
And we were having this conversation with the anthropology kids, how
They didn't want us to make noise on the way out because they were scared they're going to be next.
Yeah.
They're already there.
Got it.
Yeah.
They're trimming the fat before they get to the, yeah.
They're testing the waters.
Testing the waters.
Hmm, so I hope, yeah, I hope women in gender studies as loud as is humanly possible.
I hope these tenured professors are as loud as humanly possible.
Absolutely.
Even if it doesn't change anything for them, for the next people.
Wake up!
You think Parks and Rec at Texas A&M is filling chairs?
Right.
No.
That's a very good point.
There's so many majors here that I'm wondering.
Oh my gosh, sports management?
Like my dad?
We try to have a journalism boot, reboot.
We saw how that went.
Oh, this is some lore.
This is some old lore.
Basically under, before Welsh, we had a president.
Kathy Banks is her name?
Yes.
A hush falls over the crowd.
She basically...
They were going to redo the journalism department here at A&M.
Because I think it's telemarketing... Telecommunications and journalism is under the same department here at A&M, I think.
They pretty much want to compete with UT.
Because UT has a very prolific journalism department.
And...
They were going to bring in a tenured professor from UT to completely redo this.
It's coming together.
Yeah.
It comes out that it went from being you're going to keep your tenure to tenure track to visiting lecture.
Like it just kept winding down and winding down.
And then a group chat was leaked.
Yeah.
There's comments about the professor's race, her political affiliations, and how that is never going to stand the Texas A&M.
Kathy Banks left.
And then Mark Walshkin.
Yeah.
So.
That happened just... Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah.
What was that?
23?
23, 24?
That's even sooner than I thought.
I was taking...
I just think I remember us taking a summer film and English cross-listed class with Dr. Francis.
Yeah.
Uh-huh.
It was wonderful.
Right.
Yeah, it was a great class, but in the middle of it, this was coming out.
And being on campus during then was fascinating.
What was the general vibe?
In the English department?
Because I'm only seeing this through an English department lens.
During that class, and Dr. Francis is a black man, that doesn't feel good.
He tried to make it lighthearted and joke, and students would talk about it before class and say, that's awful.
Mm-hmm.
But I never got the rundown on how many were taking that just to get an English credit done.
I don't know.
The students were like, that's awful.
Nothing came out of it, though.
That's really sad.
No, and Kathy Banks gutted the library.
Like, Dr. Francis was, like, asking if, like, hey, can y'all rent this movie for me?
And I was like, I don't think about it.
And it's like, no, like, I'm showing it in class tomorrow.
Like, I need this reimbursed.
No, but I think...
Again, it's just trying to find excuses because that's the enemy.
It's that woke leftist ideology that would infiltrate, quote unquote, infiltrate Texas A&M, indoctrinate our students, our children.
That's always the thing, indoctrinate our children, even though most of the people talking about this do not have students at Texas A&M and they're grown ass adults, most of which did not go to college.
You do not have any skin in this game.
You have none whatsoever.
The average American does not read more than one book a year.
So who are y'all mad at?
Who are y'all mad at?
So... Yeah.
So, like, the frustration is...
Yes, yes, I'd say I think Mark Welsh was kind of that turning the new page, turning a new leaf.
I think he was making wonderful changes, like making tick a poll online.
He was talking about decreasing admissions the next five years to kind of combat the congestion that we feel in College Station and Bryan.
I think these were lovely, real conversations to be having.
And my question is, he's a retired something Starry General.
If he's not Texas A&M material,
Who is?
Who do you want?
Because picture perfect.
It's picture perfect.
So.
Because remember, he left because Republican lawmakers were giving him shit on Twitter.
saying you didn't do something fast enough when he stand by his professors and educators.
Because he acknowledged, hey, I don't have a degree in English lit.
I'm going to let her decide what's appropriate.
And that's 100% what the average boss does is acknowledging when it's not my profession.
It's just not what I know the most about.
It's a level of humility that I admired so deeply in him.
And to see that get punished.
That is sad.
Yes.
Heartbreaking.
No, and it's been boiling.
And, you know, I kept checking every day on Howdy during winter break to see if my sex and gender class was being canceled, edited, removed, what have you.
And I just kept checking it.
And, okay, I'll show up for a second class.
Okay, I'm going to show up second week class.
We'll see.
How are you living with those emotions now?
I've been carrying it mainly internally.
I have not posted anything on social media.
Cause again, then I'm a target and the history department's a target.
I'm an employee of Texas A&M.
I'm not protected by tenure.
And it's been proven that doesn't help you.
There's nothing protecting me.
And that is incredibly scary.
And again, I'm not the angry bra burning feminist that they think is taking these classes.
I'm taking these classes because indigenous peoples have different ideas of what being a woman and being a man is.
Simple as that.
Even if you were.
And even if I was, who cares?
I'm giving A&M money.
Even if you were.
Even if I were.
What's it to you?
Who is it to you?
Who is the government to say what I can and can't read?
I'm yelling.
I'm sorry.
That's fine.
Yeah, it's incredibly frustrating because it's such a slippery slope of who are you to say what can and can't be taught, what I can and can't read.
There's a definition of government overreach from the so-and-so small government party.
That's what's infuriating.
Yeah.
And to make this decision as an interim president, shame on you.
Shame on you.
Yeah.
I don't think people realize, or maybe they do, and they just don't care, that there's people behind these choices.
Not just the choices, but the effect.
That people are out of a job.
They can't feed their family.
Americans are out of jobs.
Especially in this market, this job market.
And not only that, is the students that would take these classes,
That signed up.
They were curious.
They wanted to learn something.
They said they were told, no, you can't.
You can't do that.
You can't be curious.
I know I'm supposed to be asking questions.
No, but I'm glad.
No, it's just, it's infuriating.
But I do have hope.
I see on Facebook comments, so many people are angry about this.
Mm-hmm.
So many people are angry about this, and that makes me so happy.
That it's not just people on campus.
After I just said, you know, if you don't have skin in this game, who cares?
And I completely acknowledge that's hypocritical.
But people are mad.
People are saying this is not my A&M.
I'm embarrassed to be an Aggie.
It's the same conversations OU was having a couple months ago.
Because it's antithetical to the idea of an Aggie.
Yes.
You're not respecting.
Not respecting.
No integrity.
No.
What is that?
We might have differences, but you come together, discuss it respectfully.
I think that is what an Aggie is literally bred to do when you're here.
That was one of the first things I learned was when I was reading history, that you might have differences, but you respect each other and talk about it.
Yeah, because that happens even in, I'm sure, so many ag classrooms.
Well, I think we should breed this heifer on this day.
Well, I think we should do it this day.
Mm-hmm.
That's a completely different, we're not talking about literature.
We're talking about something concrete, real that we can touch and feel, but we're still having a disagreement and we have to have a civil conversation about how to remedy that.
And that's what you're taking away.
Very much so.
Yeah.
How does this, I think I know the answer, but how does this make you feel about the future of this university?
It depends on if Abbott's re-elected, if I can be completely honest with you.
It entirely hinges upon Abbott being re-elected because with his new foreign visa ban he wants to implement, that's going to impact us.
That's going to impact UT.
It's going to impact thousands of students.
It is an honor that someone in Taiwan wants to leave their family and come here when it's 80 degrees on Christmas and humidity is 100%.
That's an honor for
And the American dream.
That is the American dream.
And you are robbing that of thousands, thousands of people.
And their families.
And it breaks my heart to know that we might lose an R1 distinction, which is the pinnacle of academic success.
We spend, I think, close to a billion dollars in research a year.
More than that.
It's put food on my table.
Mm-hmm.
Keeps my lights on.
You're impacting thousands of Americans with these decisions.
And soon to be Americans.
Yes.
So.
It's turning away people who want to be American.
Yep.
Want to be Texans.
Want to be Aggies.
Yes.
Absolutely.
100%.
So that's what I'm more worried about.
The second we lose that R1, we lose professors, we lose grad students.
Sure.
I've been jokingly encouraged to think about other places.
I think it's heartbreaking.
And something needs to change.
At a state level.
Till I go blue in the face, this is not a university level.
This is a state level decision.
There's been six flags over Texas.
So we are not a homogenous people.
I don't know where y'all got that idea from.
You go through an H-E-B, how many lines of other countries are you seeing that you can shop from?
Yep.
So.
Oh, that's very valid.
Yep, yep, yep, yep.
Thank you for sharing those things.
Yeah, of course.
Yeah.
How's the general...
We're terrified.
We're hopeful though.
It is such, it is the best of times and the worst of times, really and truly.
We are so excited.
We're hiring three new faculty this year.
So obviously there's still, there's still interest.
There's still attractiveness to be at A&M and we don't take that for granted.
We just sent out our acceptance letters for the new cohort for grad students.
That's so exciting.
So it is this very bittersweet time where we keep looking over our shoulders.
What would help this department and also just the faculty and staff in general?
Trust, feeling like we are trusted to do our jobs that we were hired to do, that we were accepted to do.
Go away with the syllabus review.
I completely understand wanting to update course descriptions.
Some of those are 50 years old.
But you're hiring someone who's an expert in a field you might know nothing about.
I would trust them any day to say what's appropriate or not to teach.
Very fair.
Yeah.
I would say that.
Or heavy, literal statement saying that we're not touching anything else.
We're good.
And this should have been done before the semester started.
Yeah, very much.
Was it two weeks?
They gave people two weeks?
Yeah.
That's not enough time.
No, right before Christmas?
Not enough time.
Are you kidding?
People don't check their email.
No.
Sorry, that's... No, no, like, no.
No, it's complete, no.
Again, you have to ask this question.
Are we a business or are we a school?
We're being treated like the former.
So, just lay off.
I think that's the thing.
Lay off.
Let me do what I need to do.
Yeah, let the school be school.
Yeah.
The people who say, what would you say to people who are, that have that fear of, they actually legitimately have that fear of you're going to indoctrinate my kids.
What would you say to them?
They've been living at your house for 20 years.
You have to trust that the morals you raised them with are gonna withstand.
And I think it is wonderful that they're being questioned, and they might come out the other end stronger in the beliefs that you taught them.
110%, that is a real possibility.
Yeah.
If you're nervous about a 16-week course completely transforming your child into an unrecognizable person,
I think you need to have lunch with your kid.
Are you talking to your student weekly?
Are you checking in on them?
Are you just sending them Venmos?
Yeah.
Are you having a real relationship with your child?
What's more important to you?
My dad said he'd rather I come home pregnant than a liberal when I went to college.
That's rough.
Yes.
That's actually been upsetting.
What's more important to you?
How your child votes?
Or how they love and respect and treat others?
I get it.
I get the idea of sending your kid off.
I find it funny that people from other states come here because I'm like, how did you hear about us?
I completely get it.
You're sending your kid thousands of miles away, hours away.
Hell, if you're in El Paso, you're not seeing your kid until Christmas.
So I completely get that.
It's just up to you to still engage because raising a child is not done once they hit 18.
That relationship doesn't dissolve just because they're in class.
So ask yourself, what's more important?
Maintain that relationship.
Have room in your mind and heart to be challenged yourself.
We're not saying you're wrong.
You're a horrible person.
You're going to burn in hell.
No one's saying that.
Difficult conversations are wonderful to have and you will come out stronger together.
I promise you.
Thank you.
I think parents right now are just, there's anxieties in the country as a whole, and they're just, what is the closest thing that resembles that right now?
What is something that I can mirror, put that on?
And I think that right now is the conversation that's closest to home for parents.
I think that's all that is.
I'm not a parent.
Me either.
I don't know.
But I think that's something that's,
no matter what side you're on, that you really need to.
Even if things make you uncomfortable, as you said.
No one's attacking you.
You know, students, if you are feeling that, you know, if your parents ask you what you're reading and you know they're not going to like something, talk it through them.
Point to things that you did like, things that you didn't like.
If you say, like, I completely disagreed with that entire book, move on.
That's 100% okay.
I've read books and I'm like, eh, the argument didn't sell me.
That's okay.
It can really be as simple as that.
Mm-hmm.
It really can be.
It doesn't have to be, I have to email the person who wrote this, demand they lose their job.
Like, no, it's not that deep.
It's really not.
I think also that people are equating what professors are teaching with what they personally believe.
Yes.
Those two things aren't the same.
No.
Like, it kind of, it frustrates me that this actually became the word and the language the university implemented when doing the syllabus reviews.
But I, on the permanent record, I said, like, educating someone is not advocating.
So then I kind of bit my tongue when that became the slogan of saying, are you advocating for these ideologies?
That's so vague.
And they did that on purpose.
It's easier to just brush everything under a rug and throw it away and light it on fire.
It's 100% easier.
How do you know if it's advocating?
Are you wearing a pride flag?
What does that look like?
It's just this vague monster that they can constantly change what looks like.
Yeah.
So that's the scariness of it.
It can constantly change what they are attacking.
And I think that's what every department needs to be scared of.
Every single department needs to be scared of.
Every department.
Okay, if one department's on the top of the box, everybody.
Yes.
And I'm not saying complete gut.
I'm saying professors.
Your citizenship status.
If you're married to the same sex.
Because they are saying one thing with this.
The public is personal and the personal is public.
That's 110% what this is.
So it's just McCarthyism.
It's neo-McCarthyism.
That's all it is.
Yeah.
No.
Nope.
Changed.
We're not the only ones that are scared.
Absolutely.
All of us are.
Yeah.
I'd be more concerned if you pulled a kid over.
Like, you know, you're waiting for the bus, the shuttles, and they have no idea what's going on.
That's concerning.
That's way worse, in my opinion, than being like, no, I'm 110% for this.
I'd rather you be 110% for this than having no idea what's going on.
Because that means you actually are reading and standing up for something.
Yeah.
Being informed.
Yep.
And that's one of the things that this university is supposed to do.
Yes.
Inform citizens.
Yep.
That is part of the land grant mission.
Exactly.
Inform citizens.
So, not that I, it is, it is very, like, we're both, same hack, we're both, we're both,
It's comforting and also very sad.
Yes.
And this directly obviously affects you because you're teaching your TA.
So how did you, whenever you got that news, what was the things that were going through your head?
I was heartbroken.
I still am.
I am heartbroken.
I did a guest lecture last semester about the 60s and 70s, and I was going to do actual social history on it.
I had slides I was making, and I had a photo of Marsha P. Johnson, and I thought, I can't.
I can't.
So I just did pop culture.
in the 60s and 70s, and I slipped some stuff in.
I was like, hey, look, the Beatles have long hair now.
But then, you know, Pharaoh in Rosemary's Baby has short hair.
What's that?
Like, you know, so I tried to make it accessible in ways that they can see concretely.
I think that was, I really tried, I tried to do that.
And...
I think another thing I strongly believe is that people who are...
against teaching about gender don't realize that the fact of even in their binary yeah to teach about binary you're still teaching gender you're still teaching you can't teach about anything i you can't teach anything you can't teach about heteronormative marriage nothing in that i can't mention i married a man
The Aggie that I met here on campus that is a master's engineering student, an exemplary Aggie, I can't mention that.
That's because that's part of you.
That's part of me.
So.
That feeling of having to leave.
Yeah.
Parts of behind.
And if you want to get technical, okay, you're telling a university that didn't widely accept women until 66, they're getting rid of women's studies.
even though A&M is mostly women today.
Oh, I didn't know that.
There's more women in college than men right now.
I think that's scaring some people.
I would say yes.
Yeah, so not a good look.
Not a good look.
How much time do you generally would put into creating those lessons?
Oh my gosh.
Three hours at least.
Because it's making slides, making sure they're accessible slides.
It's double-checking my sources.
It's so much.
And that's per lesson.
Yeah, that's per lesson.
And I only did that one guest lecture.
But they encourage new profs
to pretty much like over the summer, write all your lectures.
So you can just hit the ground running and not have to play catch up and you can do an honest job on it and not just freak out.
And I leaned on other grad students of, Hey, what'd you have during this time period that I should probably mention too.
Yeah.
So to see that
You are encouraged to make it before and you put so much time into it.
So to receive those emails.
Delete it.
Exactly.
Slap in the face.
It's a slap in the face.
I'm sorry.
No, I mean, just everyone has a gender.
Everyone has sexual orientation.
Everyone has a race.
Everyone has an ethnic, racial belonging.
These are all things you fill on the SAT.
It's okay.
It doesn't have to separate.
That's the whole point of why we're talking about it is so we can have a more cohesive and united today.
So I think that's the most infuriating thing.
And I think the line they were saying is they didn't want white kids to feel guilty.
Yeah, that was brought up a lot.
Unless your last name is Lee and you're related to Robert E.,
How would you know?
Unless your mom's a united daughter of confederacy.
Also even then.
It's one of the sins of our fathers.
And if you're so far gone, I don't think you're feeling bad sitting in class.
That's my thing.
If you are so on that spectrum, I don't think you're feeling bad.
No.
You're looking at that through nostalgia.
You're not.
No, I think...
That pisses me off.
And I'm not just saying that as a northerner.
Like, what do you mean you feel guilty?
Yeah.
You didn't do it.
You should be disgusted in your country and try to have a better tomorrow that actually fulfills the Constitution.
Mm-hmm.
That's why I kind of brought up this hard, like, how would you address this hard conversation?
Yeah.
This uncomfortable.
Because I think people also equate...
those hard conversations where they're uncomfortable needing to feel guilty those things don't need to happen those things don't need to happen you can feel guilty as an American of I'm in the South that was built in the economy of this chattel slavery empire that we were
How are we addressing that today?
It does not have to be shameful.
It does not have to be with guilt.
If we're approaching it with honesty, honestly trying to make the tomorrow better, I think that's beautiful and wonderful.
So that whole child guilt thing, how do you measure that?
Hey, raise your hand if you felt guilty.
Okay, let's go on one to 10.
Yeah.
How do you actually do that?
Again, it's this elusiveness that means nothing.
Don't give them an idea.
But no, it's this elusiveness that you cannot concretely implement in the classroom.
Yeah.
At all.
Yeah, that's not something like, it's not on the end of your... No.
No.
Yeah.
And like I said, the uncomfortable means you're human.
I'm glad you're feeling something.
If you're not feeling anything, learning about these horrific events, you're weird.
Like, that's weird.
Weird.
Yeah.
So that's my two sons.
I think it's valuable because as a historian, you see that what's happened and the patterns.
Yeah.
Yeah, they rhyme.
Because that's the first day of every history class.
It's like, why do we study history?
And without fail, a kid will raise their hand and say, so we don't repeat it.
And you just want to roll your eyes.
History doesn't repeat, it rhymes.
It's not like an exact copy.
So, but you know, happy that he rose his hand.
Happy you're here, but yeah.
Hey, that's something.
Something, yeah.
So, I want you to do something a little lighter.
Yeah.
um i was surprised by how much i enjoyed my guest lecture um i improvised some of it and you know getting back to my theatrical roots is always fulfilling um just seeing the spark the connection the the faces change when they're understanding something that's priceless that is utterly priceless um and like you know they walk out and go like that was my favorite lecture
Like, that's so special.
In terms of just loving history, I think just because it's everywhere.
You feel more connected, your country, your people.
You feel less alone, I think, because you know that people have been feeling similarly.
Mm-hmm.
since human existence like when you're reading chaucer and there's a line about jealousy or sadness or rage i'm okay because someone in 1394 felt that so i'm going to get through this so i yeah it's just the human condition i think is very very comforting yeah yeah yeah even through time yeah no you find comfort in that the people have always been people
in like bad ways but also amazing way like love is just everywhere really and truly without being really corny love is really really everywhere and that that's probably the best part that's really touching um so did you want to be a lecturer or do you want to continue your research
That's something I've been grappling with that I hope I can answer more concretely probably by the time I'm ending PhD.
I think it was easy to do that pop culture lecture because the stakes were lower.
Me talking about best picture winners versus having to explain Indian removal, I feel a lot of weight.
That feels very, very heavy responsibility-wise because I acknowledge completely that might be the only time people hear about it.
not watch it in, you know, Dances with Wolves, but truly learns about it.
So that's very daunting.
Obviously, research is fun, you know, getting unique answers and filling in gaps where people may not have ever thought about and getting a fuller picture.
That's always wonderful.
But yeah, I really, really enjoy teaching.
So we'll see.
Yeah, but I think A&M does a wonderful job, even though it is an R1.
It encourages actual education with educators, I think.
It's not just someone reading off slides.
They encourage that connection, I think.
Very much.
So whenever you personally are learning and doing your research, you have those really heavy topics.
You have that sinking feeling that you're talking about.
Yeah.
It's silly, maybe, but I wrote a paper on pretty much the legacy of Carlisle for one of my historiography classes last semester.
And I ended it with, it failed.
At the end of the day, Carlisle failed.
And I think of myself a lot, there's 572 federally recognized tribes in the US.
So every law, every broken treaty,
they fail because they're still indigenous people today and they're a modern people.
They're not stuck in the past.
That's probably what gets me through really and truly.
Yeah.
I don't think that's the way I'm all I think.
I think even if you said it was a silly thing, I don't think it's silly to have this coping mechanism.
Yeah.
I'm always interested in having people.
Yeah, or I'm not wearing it today, but I have a turquoise ring and I have a silver bangle.
It's Navajo.
And it's just, you know, these are tangible that, you know, indigenous hands made.
And there is something that, yes, they have to do that because they're in impoverished communities, our majority indigenous, but that beauty and that tradition is still with us today and is tangible.
So I would just say reminding that even though I am studying the horrors of the past, I still see the love of today very much alive.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Because that's another thing in my line of work.
I hear the most horrific things.
So yeah, sometimes I take people's
Yeah, no, yeah.
Yeah.
I think it's really, even today I'm reading a book on memorials for my, I'm doing an internship with the Journal of Texas History.
And it's a public history facing publication.
And for my internship, I have to obviously read.
I can't just like show up.
And the book's called Memorial Mania.
And they're covering, you know, Columbine.
Oh, God.
Yeah.
Girl, that's heavy as hell.
Heavy as hell.
So, you know, if it's just playing with my dog or listening to fun music, cooking dinner, like, I think it's just reconnecting with what you love today.
Very much so.
Yeah.
Very human.
Very.
Because, again, human condition.
Human condition.
Yeah.
It always has been.
Always, always.
Yeah.
There is something...
as you said, there was something super comforting to see that people experience those things and they got through it or they did something to get, you know, so.
Yeah, no, yeah.
Whether they like it or not, we're gonna get through it.
This too shall pass, whether you like it or not.
Yeah, truly.
Yeah.
So what are some of the fun things about being a graduate student?
Oh, it's this basement.
like it sounds like cruel that all of us are stuck in the basement but the people i've like um meg mcclure megan mcclure she's a fellow grad she's who i always wanted to meet in undergrad like friend wise like just amazing just completely same sense of humor like we are killing it we're the only two girls in our cohort so it's immediate like
this.
I would just say it's the people I've met, really and truly.
And it's a side of college you haven't really thought about maybe as an undergrad.
It's getting the nitty-gritty.
It's fun to not be the one sitting down but standing up, I think.
It's just getting a different perspective of the university experience, which is really, really exciting.
yeah yeah how was how was that experience of being a woman um being one of the only yeah do you you feel it you feel it sometimes um like it feels like the guys just want to talk about Iraq all the time and it's like I don't have a thing in Iraq um
You feel it sometimes.
I think it doesn't help that both of us are social historians that maybe are not as seen as prestigious compared to military history.
Yeah, it seems like the history field has dominated by specific parts of it, dominated by men.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah, that's fine.
But, you know, historically, who was allowed to learn how to read?
But that's another thing.
You want to look at frustrations today?
Okay.
Well, we can probably give you a short joke answer why that is.
But I think it's exciting to know that, you know, we're all in this together and we're going to get through it.
And it's good to have that little pact.
Right.
That ally.
I'd probably say that.
Yeah.
I try not to think about, you know, us versus them.
That's not true.
It's not a competition.
It's not.
You just, you feel it when there's one guy who is, you know, two other guys could agree with each other or say similar things.
But if Megan and I agree with each other, he'll go like, well, as the ladies have already said, but he would not do that for, you know, like whereas, you know, John Doe has already said, he would never do that.
He would just say, well, as the ladies have already said,
And it's like, actually no one was thinking about my sex, but okay, thank you.
So yeah.
So even if you don't want to think about it, it's still brought up.
Yeah.
So if they see me as that, okay.
Right.
And maybe it's because I'm not ineligible, whatever.
There's an element to that.
I'm married.
Yeah.
There's nothing there for you other than maybe companionship, platonically, but yeah.
there's something there yeah and ginger time to mix in um workspaces too is always really interesting yeah and it's you know our department head is dr hudson she's a woman she's made it very clear that anyone preying on that us women down here is not going to be handled swept under the rug whatsoever and that's very comforting yeah yeah yeah i also didn't really
Yes, she is.
Yes.
Yeah.
She's been here.
This will be her 19th year here.
Holy crap.
Yeah.
She did not.
She went to Auburn, Georgia and you know.
Okay.
I see why.
Yeah.
That makes sense.
This is all coming together.
Yeah.
me that of like also like when how women experience position different positions too like like I'm sure her experience is so much so different from like 19 years ago to now oh yeah oh yeah oh yeah and you know I think a lot of it is also the aspect that we're in a smaller subfield
Indigenous studies really didn't come to be a respected, renowned, maybe until the 80s or 90s.
And even then we're still fighting for space.
So, yeah, I would probably argue maybe my peers see me less because of that, not because of my sex.
I'd say that.
It's...
So what is the, you said Iraq, so are most of the other people here military?
We have a military, in my cohort specifically, we have military, he's active in the Marine Corps.
Yeah, the government's paying for him to be here.
And then we have a diplomat history.
Um, and then we have another social, we have a guy working in the Philippines in World War II with like POWs.
Um, we have another social historian.
So yeah, it's mainly just the ones who are loud as hell are a diplomatic in our military.
Um, who the latter has been, no, the diplomatic has been very loud about not valuing social history as worth his time.
Yeah.
Yeah, but then he wrote a paper about the social history of World War 12, or 1812, and we were like, why the change of heart?
It's weird.
Yeah.
It's not interesting.
I try to limit my time with him.
Yeah, that's fair.
Yeah.
No, but I'd say we're all doing different things.
I would say there's not a lot of, there's almost no overlap.
between anyone doing any topic, yeah.
That's kind of good though, because no one steps on each other.
It's wonderful.
There's only one other indigenous guy and he's doing his PhD and he's like colonial times.
So like we are not at the, no, I'm Jim Crow.
He's colonial.
Like we, we do not.
Yeah.
Very different.
Cause I know, um, researchers can also be like super territorial.
Yeah.
I don't own these people.
I don't know these people.
I spent a year researching them at the end of the day.
I never met him.
He's been dead since the 60s.
I don't know him.
kind of remind I don't know these people I don't own these people I don't own their stories yeah I am finding fragments of their life and trying to connect those that is all that is all yeah yeah it's more just you're interacting with it and appreciating it and then
moving on.
Yeah.
You put it so well.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you.
Yes.
Yeah.
Another broader question.
So you've been here for almost 10 years.
What are some changes in just like the culture or the culture on campus or the student life or anything like that have you seen?
They think there is a housing crisis.
They being the city of College Station.
That's not true.
This is a lie.
They are tearing, you know, building these high rises that are going to be, you know, $1,600 a month to live with six other people.
And it's very frustrating because who's that helping?
Not Brian's citizens who aren't affiliated with the college.
You're tearing down small businesses owned by ags to build these skyscrapers
For kids who probably don't even need to live on Northgate.
Because part of the reason why you can charge so much being on Northgate is because you're by the bars.
So tearing down bars isn't going to help you.
No.
And I'd say, unfortunately, I'm very disconnected to undergrad life.
Um...
That tracks.
I think you're seeing a lot of athleisure on campus.
I'm ready for that to be done.
I'm ready for kids to start dressing in jeans and neutral clothes as a whole.
I haven't seen a lot of online shopping during my TA class that semester, so that's exciting.
It's also early, though.
I don't know what that would look like on spring break.
I think the chat GPT of it all is going to be fascinating.
Yeah.
That's going to be fascinating.
That's something I wanted to bring up too.
I don't interact.
I don't interact with it.
As a library, the higher-ups wanted us to see if we could use AI in our daily life.
A lot of us, especially in Cushing, are against it because that's directly taken our jobs.
Yes.
And creating more work.
Yeah.
AI can't pull boxes for you and wheel them into the Cush and Kelsey reading room.
That can't happen.
No.
So I'm interested, like, how is the student side?
Yeah.
I think in the next five years, we'll see a complete push to online physical paper exams.
I firmly believe that.
Oh, to physical paper?
Yes.
Okay.
I think we're going to completely see.
It's going to go completely analog.
Yeah.
I'm 100% for it.
Why are you spending tens of thousands of dollars to plug it into a computer?
If you're a comm major, shouldn't you know how to write efficiently?
If you're an ag major, shouldn't you know the dosage to tranquilize a horse?
Yeah.
What scares me is the, just, first of all, no regulation.
No regulation.
Second of all,
that it just makes stuff up.
They create sources.
They will bring stuff up.
I think a lot of professors are getting smarter with how to combat it.
They are saying, you can only use stuff we talked about in the documentary, this specific reading, things we talked about in the lecture, that we're doing Turn It In, that it flags AI.
I would rather, and I experienced this that first round of submissions I had to grade recently,
I was so happy reading an incoherent paragraph because I knew he wrote it.
I'd rather give him line by line edits than just give a hundred to an encyclopedia that made half it up.
So I think if you're just honest with kids and showing them like, well, it makes up sources.
I know when you use it, if you bring up this random thing, I specifically did not talk about because I wrote my lecture and
You're going to get caught.
And I think it's up to the university for being strict when it comes up and not a slap on the wrist.
Yeah, they need to do something.
Aggie does not cheat, steal, or lie.
And I think the university does not have a homogenous stance on it either.
Some departments you can use it, some you can't.
And I do think we're being more upfront about it on that first syllabus day of like, hey, in this class you can't use it whatsoever.
Mm-hmm.
But again, I'm not in the headspace of someone who uses it.
Right.
So I don't know if that's a deal breaker.
I don't know if that's like, well, that's fine if I can use it for other classes.
I have no idea.
I'm just not in that headspace because I can't do what I need to do with JAT-GPT.
I'm creating original research.
Right, yeah.
You're the one.
You're the creator.
I'm the creator that's going to get ripped off.
Yeah.
Like, no.
That's my...
Forget about the environmental, forget about the social impact.
Yeah.
The theft is like...
It's the theft.
Yeah.
Not that those things don't matter because I care about... Yeah, I care about... No, it's the death of the individual.
It's the death of the cognizant, whatever.
It's a long tangent.
It's very interconnected to mass consumerism.
A lot of buzzwords.
It's... Yeah.
Yeah.
I do view people less when I find out they use it for everyday life.
I don't care.
Why are you asking it to make you a recipe?